I'll never forget his words. He said,
"Something terrible is going to happen."
We're hearing camp commanders on the
phone with their students and they're
crying and saying, "I'll see you in
paradise." And he said, "I'm begging
you. If you have any sources inside
al-Qaeda, please help us.
I was recruited by the CIA beginning in
the late 1980s, but in a very odd way
that is no longer legal. Um, I was in
graduate school at George Washington
University in Washington DC. And I was
taking a class called the psychology of
leadership that was taught by an eminent
psychiatrist by the name of Dr. Gerald
Post. Um, Dr. The post gave us an
assignment one day where we had to
shadow our bosses and write a
psychological evaluation of our bosses.
And um I was shadowing my boss and he
was a he was a very difficult,
mean, unpleasant, strong, brutish kind
of person. And I went back to my
apartment and I wrote my paper and I
said that he was a sociopath with
psychopathic and possibly violent
tendencies. I gave Dr. Post the paper
and a week later he gives it back to me
and he gave me an A and underneath the A
he wrote, "Please see me after class."
So I went to see him and I said, "Dr.
Post, you wanted to see me." He said,
"Come to my office." So we went
downstairs in the building into his
little academics office. He closed the
door and he said, "Look, I'm not really
a professor here. I'm a CIA officer
undercover as a professor here and I'm
looking for people who would fit into
the CIA's culture. I think you would fit
in. Do you want to be a CIA officer?
And I said yes.
And so he made some calls. It was up to
me to pass all the tests and there were
a lot of tests, but that's how I got
into the CIA. And I guess when you first
joined the CIA, what was the global
political landscape like? and what was
the US's stance with their foreign
policy? When I joined the CIA, the
Soviet Union was literally in the
process of collapsing.
And so all eyes were on Eastern Europe.
My expertise was in the Middle East. I
had a bachelor's degree in Middle
Eastern studies. I had studied um
Islamic theology with one of the the
leading uh Muslim scholars in the West.
and uh and my master's degree was in uh
focused in foreign policy analysis. So I
was very specific about the Middle East
and so I was assigned to Iraq and um I
immediately became Saddam Hussein's
classified biographer in the
intelligence community. So, while the
Soviet Union is falling apart and those
analysts are becoming big stars, I
focused on Iraq. And then, much to my
shock and the world's shock, nine months
later, Iraq invaded Kuwait and overthrew
the Kuwaiti royal family and seized
Kuwait's oil fields. Uh, this was a
naked act of aggression and war. And so,
um, I walked in that morning. I got up
early because we knew that the invasion
was coming. We predicted 30 days before
that Saddam would invade Kuwait. But um
I got into the office early and my boss
u sort of intercepted me and said,
"Don't take your jacket off. We're going
to the White House." And I had never
been to the White House before. So we we
got in a car. We drove to the White
House. And we were escorted into the
Oval Office. And keep in mind, I was 25
years old at the time. And you walk into
the Oval Office and here's the
president, the vice president, the
national security adviser, the CIA
director, my boss, and me. And the the
mood is very heavy. So everybody sits
down and the president says, "Well, now
what do we do?" And then everybody turns
and looks at me.
And it took me a second to get my
bearings. And I said, "Well, the Kuwaiti
government's been overthrown. The Iraqi
government announced this morning that
they had installed Ahmed al- Khatib as
the occupation governor of Kuwait. I
said, "Unfortunately,
we happen to know a lot about Ahmed
Khib. He got a medical degree at the
American University of Beirut and his
college roommate was George Habash. And
together they created the Popular Front
for the Liberation of Palestine." And
the vice president says, "Jesus Christ."
And I thought, "Wow, this is this is
bad." We finished the briefing, got up
and walked out. And two things happened.
My boss said to me,
"There's something you need to
understand." He said, "I'm not sure that
you're appreciating the importance of
what's happening. It's not unusual for a
country that we cover to go to war. It's
highly unusual for a country that we
cover to go to war with us."
And then later that afternoon, Margaret
Thatcher, who at the time was the
British Prime Minister, called the
president, it was George HW Bush, and
famously told him, these were her words,
"Now's not the time to go wobbly,
George."
And that call
was like a wakeup call for George HW
Bush. And so
we sent the largest army deployed since
the end of the Vietnam War. We invaded
Kuwait. We liberated it and then uh the
rest is history.
You were then stationed in the Middle
East. What was your role out there? I
served first in Saudi Arabia, then in
Kuwait, and then I went back to
headquarters for a while and decided
that that I so loved serving overseas
that I wanted to do it on a longer term
basis. So, I applied for uh what's
called a rotation uh at the State
Department. And I this was an honest to
god state department job where I left
the CIA and I went to the State
Department. Um, I was sworn in as a
foreign service officer and I became the
economic officer at the American embassy
in Bahrain for two years and then back
to headquarters to work on Iraq again.
But I did get bored after seven and a
half years of Iraq, Iraq, Iraq, every
single day Iraq. And so I made a very
unusual
transition
from intelligence to operations and
specifically to counterterrorist
operations.
And what does that mean? So as an
analyst,
your job is to sit in a cubicle, read
all source intelligence that's coming in
from all over the world, think the big
thoughts, write papers that probably
nobody will ever read. Once or twice a
week, you write something for the
president if it's important enough to
merit his attention and then you go home
at the end of the day. Counterterrorism
operations was what you see in the
movies. I went straight into weapons.
And then after weapons, I went into
explosives. After explosives, I went
into counterterrorist driving. And then
advanced counterterrorist driving, which
was out in the desert out west. And then
you learn how to spot, assess, develop,
and recruit spies to steal secrets.
And what year was this? That was 1997.
And was there any other time in these
years that you were questioning the
ethics of the agency and the work you
were doing? No, I didn't question the
ethics uh of the agency at the time for
for a very specific reason. When Bill
Clinton was elected president,
he issued an order that the CIA had to
what they called cull their recruited
assets. Anybody who had
what the White House described as a
human rights problem was to be fired.
Right? So, we didn't want to do business
anymore in the 1990s with death squad
leaders or assassins.
Uh, and Clinton was serious about that.
And I remember saying to a colleague at
the time, I can't believe they're
actually serious about human rights.
This is really a very pleasant surprise
for me. But Bill Clinton wasn't
president forever. He was only president
for eight years. And then 911 happened
and literally everything changed in the
blink of an eye.
So in 2001, where were you working? What
was your what was your role at that
time? In 2001, I had just returned from
my first overseas operational tour in
Athens. and I was working in
headquarters and my job was to train
Middle Eastern intelligence services in
how to carry out counterterrorism
operations. And so, um, I had to go to
the White House on the morning of
September 11th, 2001
with the director of the CIA's
counterterrorism center, Ambassador
Kofer Black. And um I walked over to his
office to tell him that our car was
ready to take us to the White House. And
when I got there, uh his secretary had a
small TV on her desk because you
couldn't watch TV on your computers back
then. And the news was on and one of the
towers of the World Trade Center was
burning. And I said, "What happened to
the World Trade Center?" She said, "A
plane had flown into it." And I said,
"Ah, well, you know, that happened once
before in 1932. A plane flew into the
Empire State Building, but it was really
raining and very foggy that day. It's so
clear today. How can you not see that
you're flying into the World Trade
Center?" And as soon as I said it, the
second plane hit. And she turned to me
and she said, "Did you see that or did I
imagine it?" And I ran back to my office
and I said, "Guys, two planes just hit
both towers of the World Trade Center. I
think we're under attack." And then
everybody ran up to the director's
office, TVs all over the place, and
we're all just standing there. And then
the third plane hits the Pentagon.
There was a an officer from the CIA
police for we have our own internal
police force. Uh and he came in and he
said, "Everybody evacuate right now.
Everybody evacuate. Nobody budged. We
just stood there. And then finally,
somebody shouted behind me. Somebody
shouted, "Will someone please lead?" And
Kofheer said, "Oh, uh, yeah, you go to
the director's office and tell him this.
You go to security and tell him that.
You go up to operations." And, you know,
so everybody started to scramble. The
rest of us are just standing there. And
then finally a guy said to me, a guy I
was standing next to, he said, "There's
still a plane in the air and I think we
should probably assume that it's coming
here."
So my girlfriend, who later became my
wife, she was also a senior CIA officer,
she met me at my apartment and we went
to the roof and we watched the Pentagon
burn for an hour and then she said, "We
should try to donate blood."
So we we went. There were blood mobiles
uh all over the place, but the lines
were so long they told us it'll be 24
hours before they could clear the line.
And I said to her, "This is ridiculous.
We have to go back to work." So I walked
back to my car, drove across the grassy
median, drove back to the CIA, and then
I I didn't leave for 4 days. I just
balled up my jacket and I I slept under
my desk. And I guess from that point, it
changed everything. It changed literally
everything. I remember saying to a
colleague,
"Do they realize what they've done?" I
mean, I get that this group wants to
strike a blow to US hijgemony and the
empire. I get it.
But do they know nothing from history?
Do they not know that our response is
going to be a thousand times
what they did to us? And certainly, you
know, we spent altogether in the
so-called war on terror, we spent 23
trillion dollars
and we killed as many as 2 million
people.
Did they not see that coming? Osama bin
Laden said later that he wanted to
damage the US economy. He failed
and he was responsible then for you know
the deaths of an untold number of
people. What did he think he was really
going to accomplish?
So it was a failure all around and
changed the world permanently and who
was Osama bin Laden and what was his
intention?
The bin Laden family is a very honorable
um very highly respected family.
Dozens of them live permanently in the
United States. They have billions and
billions of dollars and they have made
that money through bin Laden industries.
So Osama bin Laden
who had vacationed as a teenager in the
United States and all over Western
Europe and and was very Americanized
self-radicalized after the Soviet Union
invaded Afghanistan in 1979. He went to
Afghanistan
um in the late 1980s
to fight the Soviets.
He was the only member of his family
that self-radicalized. Everybody else,
you know, lived the good life in France,
in the UK, and in the United States. And
so, um,
he came up on our radar as somebody who
was potentially dangerous. I sat next to
a guy when I first got hired and in the
summer of 1990 he wrote a paper saying
that he believed Osama bin Laden was the
most dangerous man in the world. And I
remember saying who
I never heard of this guy. And he said
buddy this is one bad guy. Watch and
see. Watch and see. Well, five years
later, I'm living in Bahrain. I'm at
lunch in the embassy cafeteria and the
TV is on and here there's a terrorist
attack in Dahran, Saudi Arabia at a
facility called um OPM Sang. This was a
a joint facility of the US military and
the Saudi Arabian National Guard. and
terrorists had gotten onto the base and
had killed something like five people
and I think they were all uh third
country nationals. I think they were
Indians.
So
this group called al-Qaeda took
responsibility for this attack. Nobody
had ever heard of al-Qaeda. So the
Saudis did what the Saudis do and they
rounded up a dozen and a half people.
They all confessed using the identical
language on national TV and they were
all immediately beheaded.
Some of them may have had something to
do with the attack. Some of them
probably didn't have anything to do with
the attack, but certainly the
masterminds of this attack got away. Bin
Laden being the one. And he went to
Afghanistan.
Well, in Afghanistan, with the fall of
the pro-soiet uh communist government
and the advent of a Taliban government,
he was free to do anything he wanted.
And so he ordered uh that uh his
underlings create two training camps in
southern Afghanistan, one in Kandahar
province and one in Helmund province. By
2001,
al-Qaeda had carried out several
largecale attacks and we said, "Well,
we've got to get on the stick and we
have to find this guy and we have to
stop him." So, the FBI began
investigating so that he could be
charged with a crime. The CIA began
looking for him. We knew that he was
somewhere in Afghanistan, probably in
Kandahar, but but it was impossible to
really find him.
And then
on July the 6th, 2001,
I was at CIA headquarters and
I was entertaining a a delegation from a
Middle Eastern intelligence service. We
did this literally every single day. I
had arranged a a briefing on al-Qaeda
with a young like 23-year-old
uh analyst. So, I said, "Well, we're
going to start off today with uh a
briefing on al-Qaeda."
The door opens and Ambassador Black
walks in with the chief of operations
for the Osama bin Laden group. And I was
so shocked. I stood up and I said, "Oh."
I said, "Gentlemen, this is Ambassador
Kofer Black. He is the CIA's director of
counterterrorism and this is the
director of operations for our Osama bin
Laden group." and he sat down and I'll
never forget his words. He
said,"Something terrible is going to
happen. We don't know when and we don't
know where, but we know it's going to be
an attack on a massive scale.
We're hearing code words for a huge
attack. The honey salesman is coming
with vast quantities of honey. There's
going to be a great wedding. There's
going to be a great football match."
These are all code words for an attack.
Um, he said, "We're hearing camp
commanders on the phone with their
students and they're crying and saying,
I'll see you in paradise."
And he said, "I'm begging you. If you
have any sources inside al-Qaeda, please
help us." They were just as shocked by
this briefing as I was. They didn't say
anything. He got up. He shook their
hands. They walked out. At the end of
the day, I sent these guys back to their
hotel. It was going to be a few hours
before dinner. So, I went to Kofer's
office to thank him for spending the
time. I said, "Keofer, I have to ask
you. I'm not working on al-Qaeda. Did
you say that just for their benefit or
were you serious?" And he said, "Oh, I
was deadly serious. Something terrible
is going to happen." And then sure
enough, two months later, there it was.
From that moment after September 11th,
you were very involved in tracking down
senior members of al-Qaeda. How did that
work? Well, like everybody in the
building, I volunteered to go to
Afghanistan on September 12th,
and I volunteered again and again and
again, four times, and they kept putting
me off. Well, I was one of only 16
fluent Arabic speakers at the CIA at the
time. I had worked years earlier for the
deputy director of the counterterrorism
center. So I considered him to be a
friend. I went into his office and I
made a bold and completely empty threat.
And I said, "If you don't send me to
Afghanistan right now, I am going
straight to Exxon with my Arabic and I'm
not looking back." And he says, "Take it
easy. Take it easy.
Can you go to Pakistan?" And I said,
"Yes. When?" He said, "Tomorrow." I
said, 'Yes. What do you want me to do
there? He said, 'I want you to be the
chief of counterterrorism operations.' I
said, 'Fine.' And so I left the next
day. I arrived at in Islamabad at 4:00
in the morning. And then the driver
said, "I'll pick you up at 7:00 to take
you in the office." And I said, "Oh my
god, please. I can't sleep on planes. I
haven't slept since I left Washington.
It's been 24 hours. Let me have another
hour. Pick me up at 8." So he picked me
up at 8. I was like a zombie. And I went
in and introduced myself to the chief
and I said, "I'm I'm your new chief of
counterterrorism." And he said, "Okay,
have a seat." So he said, "Here's what I
want you to do today. I want you to come
up with a standard operating procedure
to take down a terrorist safe house."
And I said, "Okay." So I went back to my
office and I sat with a legal pad and a
pen and I thought, "Okay, if I were
going to take down a terrorist safe
house, how would I do that? And then I
thought, hm, I would want it to be dark.
I wouldn't want anybody to see me. So, I
wrote 0200 at the top of the paper. And
then I thought, I need weapons. Like
lots of weapons. I bought guns,
ammunition,
night vision goggles, battering rams,
bulletproof vests, knives,
walkietalkies
from scratch. We started this thing. And
I thought, well, 911 is an open criminal
investigation. So I have to invite the
FBI.
And this is Pakistan. It is their
country after all. So I have to invite
the Pakistanis.
So I wrote, you know, joint team, CIA,
FBI, ISI with the list of weapons. I
ordered the weapons. They were there,
you know, in days. So a week later, we
did our first test raid. We caught two
al-Qaeda fighters. Another few days
later, we we caught an actual mid-level
guy from Egyptian Islamic Jihad. It
worked. And then finally, six weeks
later, we get word from a sister agency
in uh the Washington suburbs that Abu
Zuba, who we believed at the time was
the number three in al-Qaeda, was
somewhere in Pakistan, and we had to
catch him. That was all we knew. He was
somewhere in Pakistan. And I said in our
morning meeting, I said, "This country
is the size of Texas. It has 220 million
people in. What do you mean he's in
Pakistan? Go catch him.
But we came up with a plan and and we
caught him. He was shot three times and
severely wounded. So um I sat with Abu
Zuba for 56 hours um after we we shot
him. The the Pakistani doctors there
saved his life pumping blood into him as
quickly as they could. It was just
oozing out of him, pooling underneath
the bed. He was soaked in blood. We were
soaked in blood. It was like a scene out
of a horror movie. But um but he lived.
And then finally he asked me, "What's
going to happen to me?" And I said,
"Honestly, I don't know, but I'm going
to give you some advice." I said, "I am
the nicest guy that you're going to meet
in this experience. my colleagues,
they're not nice like I am. So, if you
do one thing, it's that you have to
cooperate.
And he said, "You seem like a nice man,
but you're the enemy, and I'll never
cooperate."
Finally, a a CIA jet flew in. And three
FBI agents and I
picked up his gurnie and carried him out
to the plane. He was crying. He asked if
I would hold his hand, which I did. We
had to maneuver him. We had to stand him
up on the gurnie. He was strapped down
to maneuver him onto the plane. We laid
him on the luggage rack at the back of
the plane and tied him down. And he
squeezed my hand and I said, "Remember,
you have to cooperate."
And then he flew off. Well, a few weeks
later, I flew back to headquarters and I
was in the cafeteria one day just
standing in the sandwich line and a
senior officer walked up to me and said
very casually, "Hey, I'm so glad I ran
into you. Um, do you want to be
certified in the use of enhanced
interrogation techniques?" And I had
never heard that term before. This was
May of 2002.
I said, "What's that mean?" And he says,
"We're going to start getting rough with
these guys." And I said, 'What does that
mean? And he described these 10
techniques. And I said, I said, 'Th that
sounds like a torture program. And he
said, 'It's not torture. The Justice
Department approved it and the president
signed it. We're going to start soon.
You are you want to you want to be in?
And I said, uh, let me think about it. I
consulted a very senior officer, went
back downstairs, and I said, this is a
torture program. I have an ethical and
moral problem with it. I think it's
illegal and I'm not interested.
Well, of the 14 people that they
approached, I was the only one who said
no. And on August the 2nd,
2002,
CIA began to torture Abu Zuba and they
tortured him mercilessly.
And what method of torture were they?
Well, they were supposed to start off
with the least dangerous and least
offensive technique, which was called
the attention grabb where you grab him
by the shirt and give him a shake and
say, "Answer my questions." And it gets
gradually worse from there. But they
didn't do that. They started with the
worst technique, water boarding. They
strapped him down to a board. His feet
were elevated compared to his his head.
They put some material cloth around his
his uh face and in his mouth and then
started pouring water on his face. They
did this 87 times
and he actually drowned at one point.
His heart stopped and then they revived
him just so that they could torture him
more. Was Abu Zubed the first? Abu
Zubeda was the first. He was the test
case. And in a very rapid succession, we
we caught some of the most important
leaders of al-Qaeda. We we caught Khalid
Shik Muhammad who was the mastermind of
the 9/11 attacks. Um he was waterboarded
100 was Abu Zaba was 83 times and uh
Khaled Shik Muhammad was waterboarded
187 times. We we used other techniques
that I even believed were worse than
waterboarding. We used one uh called the
cold cell where we strip the prisoner
naked and then chain him to an eyebolt
in the ceiling so he can't sit or lay or
get comfortable in any way. And uh we
chill the cell to 50° Fahrenheit and
then every hour a CIA officer throws a
bucket of ice water on him. We murdered
two prisoners with that technique. They
died of hypothermia and then were just
buried there on the grounds unmarked.
There was another technique called uh
sleep deprivation, right? We all know
what sleep deprivation is. But what they
did in this case was they strip you
naked, chain you to that eyebolt in the
ceiling again, and then have these
industrial strength lights on you and
loud acid rock, you know, death metal
music 24 hours a day. We know from the
American Psychological Association that
people begin to to lose their minds at
day seven and they begin to die at day
nine. Your organs shut down. The CIA
kept people awake as long as 12 days and
people did lose their minds. So it just
got worse and worse and worse and I kept
waiting for somebody to say something.
These techniques were successful in
gathering intelligence. Well, see that's
the thing is all of these techniques
were unsuccessful in gathering
intelligence.
The the the intelligence that we
gathered successfully was intelligence
gathered by the FBI in the person of Ali
Sufan who was an FBI agent who used the
tried andrue FBI technique of
establishing a rapport with the
prisoner, a relationship. You offer him
a cup of tea, a cigarette, an orange, a
piece of paper to write a letter to his
mother. You don't beat him and torture
him and kill him. And so under Ali's,
you know, guidance, Abu Zubeda gave us
actionable intelligence that saved
American lives and the CIA would start
torturing him and he would go completely
silent. So, it was not just wrong
ethically and and and legally,
but it didn't work. If anything, it just
made the situation worse.
What was the turning point that made you
decide to go public about this torture
program? This program was so clearly
wrong to me that I I anticipated someone
going public and no one went public.
Well, I resigned from the CIA uh
effective spring of 2005 and uh went
into the private sector. In December of
2007, I got a call from a a reporter
from uh ABC News, which is one of the
major news or major networks in the
United States, the American Broadcasting
Corporation. And this journalist said
that he had a source who said that I had
tortured Abu Zuba. I said that was
absolutely not true. I was the only
person who was kind to Abu Zuba. And he
said, "Well, you're welcome to come on
the show and defend yourself." I didn't
know that was a reporter's trick. I'd
never spoken to a reporter before. I
said, "Yeah, I'll think about it." Well,
two days later, President Bush gives a
press conference in which he looks in
the camera and he says, "We do not
torture like that." And I said to my
wife, he is a bald-faced liar. He's
looking the American people in the eye
and he's lying. And then two days later,
he was walking to the helicopter to fly
to Camp David. And reporters always
shout questions at the president when
he's walking in the helicopter. And
usually he just goes like this, like he
can't hear, and waves. They can always
hear. So a reporter shouts a question
about torture. And he turns and he says,
"Well, if there is torture, it's because
of a rogue CIA officer." And I said to
my wife, "Brian Ross's source is at the
White House and they're going to try to
pin this on me because they were angry
that I was the only one that declined."
So I called the reporter, Brian Ross,
and I said, "I'll give you your
interview." And I decided in the days
leading up to it that I was simply going
to tell the truth. No matter what he
asked me, I was just going to tell the
truth. And that's what I did.
And what truth was that?
The truth was the CIA was torturing its
prisoners. Torture was official US
government policy. It was not the result
of a rogue. And the policy had been
personally approved by the president. So
the FBI began investigating me at the
CIA's behest. They investigated me for
an entire year from December of 2007 to
December of 2008. and they determined
that I had not committed a crime, that
torture was illegal, and it is illegal
to classify an illegality.
And so they said, "No, you're free to
go." So my wife and I actually went out
that night to celebrate.
Three weeks later, Barack Obama became
president and he named John Brennan as
the deputy national security adviser for
counterterrorism. John and I always
hated each other and I didn't know that
John asked the Justice Department to
secretly reopen the case against me. So
for the next three years, my phones were
tapped, my emails were intercepted, and
teams of FBI agents followed me
everywhere I went. Finally, in January
of 2012, I was arrested and charged with
five felonies, including three counts of
espionage. Espionage can be a death
penalty offense.
And so
I had to fight. I was confident in my
heart that I had done nothing wrong. Uh
the espionage charges were thrown out. I
hadn't committed espionage, but I had
five children at home and
uh I had gone bankrupt because of the
legal fees. I actually still owe my
attorneys $1,150,000
that they'll never see. I'll never have
that money to pay them. And so the
Justice Department does what it does. Uh
and they offered me a deal. I was facing
45 years. They offered me 23 months
and I actually turned it down. And my
lead attorney
got right in my face and he said, "You
know what your problem is? Your problem
is you think this is about justice and
it's not about justice. It's about
mitigating damage. Take the deal."
Well, I had done some research and I
found a study by um ProPublica that
found that the government wins 98.2%
of its cases. and he said, "Do you
really want to roll the dice?" So, I
took the deal.
And you served those 23 months. I served
every single day of those 23 months.
Every day. Well, first of all, I should
say I have zero regrets. Somebody had to
say something.
Zero regrets because
I wanted to be able to sleep at night. I
wanted my children to be proud of me and
I didn't want future generations to say,
you know, that Kiryaku guy, he could
have stopped this and he didn't. You
what kind of person is that? I wanted to
be on the right side of this. I knew
what was right and wrong. It was clear.
It was obvious. There were a lot of bad
guys in very senior important roles at
the CIA. I had to counter that. And you
know, I said also that these CIA people,
if they thought that prison was going to
cow me, was going to silence me, they
didn't know me at all.
So, in my view, I won.
And you think it's had an impact on the
way the CIA operates now? It has
absolutely definitely had an impact. In
fact, when Gina Haspel became the CIA
director during the first Trump
administration, we used to call her
Bloody Gina because she was the the
godmother of the torture program. In her
confirmation hearings before the Senate
Select Committee on Intelligence, she
said that the torture program was wrong
and that she wished she had nothing to
do with it.
And I said, I I call that a victory.
and any intelligence officer or anyone
that kind of witnesses wrongdoing and
they they want to speak out, what advice
would you give to someone?
You have to go with your conscience. The
CIA likes for its officers to believe
that everything in life is a shade of
gray. And that's just simply not true.
Some things in life are black and white,
right and wrong. And deep down we know
what's right and what's wrong. So trust
yourself, trust your judgment, even if
you know there's going to be fallout.
[Music]
We knew that we were being hunted by the
special branch secret police and also by
MI5. We were pretty high level targets
at that point. So we knew the extent of
the resources they could use against us.
We knew that the flat was probably
bugged. Electronic communications were
bugged. computers, phones, that sort of
thing. Um, we knew there was a
possibility we might be followed around
on the streets.